Firm and safe.
Today's דף Daf is דף י"ח, Daf Yud Chet, 18, and we
pick up at the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב'. Yud Zayin Amud
Bet. And we are in the middle of
the second פרק Perek where the focus is about what are you
allowed to do in your property and what you have to
stay away from the boundary line in order to not indirectly cause
damage or disruption in your friend's property. So the focus right now
is the משנה Mishna that said that when you make a cistern
in your property, because that can weaken the ground and so on,
if somebody has a cistern in their property, then you are not
allowed to make a similar type of a cistern or a ditch
or things that contain water in yours because that will weaken the
ground of their cistern and
you have to stay שלושה טפחים Shlosha Tefachim away. And the question,
the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava is the simple sense
of that משנה Mishna is that you only have to be distant
if the person has already built a cistern. But if there's nothing
that the person has built, you would be able to build your
thing right at the boundary line. That's one approach. And the other
approach is no, the משנה Mishna does not meant to be limited
that way. Even if nothing is built on your friend's boundary line,
you have to stay your שלושה טפחים Shlosha Tefachim away from the
boundary line in order that to not to compromise their ability to
build. So that is the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava.
That אביי Abaye says that if there's nothing that your building project
is near, you can go right up to the boundary line, and
רבא Rava says you have to remain distant from the boundary line.
So now the גמרא Gemara picks up at the bottom of י"ז
עמוד ב'. Yud Zayin Amud Bet. It is about six lines from
the bottom. תא שמע, Ta Shma, coming here, seven lines from the
bottom. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come here. סלע הבאה בידיים, Sela HaBa'ah
BeYadayim, let's say this interesting phrase, a rock that comes in the
hand, basically it means the ground is so soft that you can
basically dig it with your hands. Okay, so you have extremely soft
ground. זה חופר בורו מכאן וזה חופר בורו מכאן, Zeh Chofer Boro
Mi-kan Ve-zeh Chofer Boro Mi-kan, each person has a right to build
a cistern in their property.
זה מרחיק שלושה טפחים וסד בסיד, Zeh Marchik Shlosha Tefachim Ve-sad Be-sid,
this one has to stay שלושה טפחים Shlosha Tefachim away from the
boundary line, וזה מרחיק שלושה טפחים וסד בסיד, Ve-zeh Marchik Shlosha Tefachim
Ve-sad Be-sid, and this one has to stay שלושה טפחים Shlosha Tefachim
away from the boundary line. So you see it says that even
with that you have to be distant from the boundary line
even before the other person has already built a cistern. Every person
has a fundamental obligation to stay distant from the boundary line. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no. The גמרא Gemara says הבאה בידיים שאני.
HaBa'ah BeYadayim Shani. No, no, no, that's different. You're dealing with such
soft ground that
any person's cistern is basically fundamentally weaker and therefore you there need
to be extra precautions, but that would not necessarily be true if
we were dealing with good solid ground, then maybe you could build
right up to the boundary line. So the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי מאי קא רמי ליה? I Hachi Mai Ka Rami Lei? You're
right, that's so obvious, the case here is talking about very soft
ground. Clearly, that's what makes this a special הלכה. Halacha. So what
were you thinking that you thought that this was evidence that you
always have to stay distant from the boundary line? So the גמרא
Gemara says הבאה בידיים איצטריכא ליה. HaBa'ah BeYadayim Itztricha Lei. No, no,
no, we thought that this rule was true about all cases, you
have to be distant from the boundary line. So why then did
it take the case specifically with soft ground? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
Da'atcha Amina, because I would have thought to say כיון דהבאה בידיים,
Kivan De-hava'ah BeYadayim, if it's so soft, לבעי נמי רווחא טפי, Liba'ei
Nami Rivcha Tuvei, that maybe שלושה טפחים Shlosha Tefachim isn't enough, maybe
you need, I don't know, עשרה טפחים, Asara Tefachim, ארבע אמות. Arba
Amot. קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan that even שלושה טפחים Shlosha
Tefachim is enough. But we were assuming that the basic requirement, the
חידוש Chidush there is it's enough to do
שלושה טפחים, Shlosha Tefachim, but the basic requirement to do שלושה טפחים
Shlosha Tefachim from the boundary line, we assumed apply to everyone regardless
of the case and even if the other person did not yet
have a cistern. So we do not yet have a proof whether
you have to keep distant from the boundary line if there is
no cistern or other things that is being threatened on the immediate
other side. תא שמע, Ta Shma, come here. Last line of
י"ז עמוד ב'. Yud Zayin Amud Bet. מרחיקין את הגפת ואת הזבל
ואת המלח ואת הסיד ואת הסלעים. Marchikin Et Ha-gefet Ve-et Ha-zevel Ve-et
Ha-melach Ve-et Ha-sid Ve-et Ha-sla'im. So this is the משנה. Mishna. Other
things you have to keep away because they create heat and they
could damage a person's wall. So this is either
the leftover stuff from the olive press or the excrement or salt
or plaster or certain types of rocks that give off heat. מכותלו
של חבירו, Mi-kotlo Shel Chaveiro, you have to keep it away from
your friend's wall because it'll give off heat and damage the wall,
ג' טפחים. Gimel Tefachim. או סד בסיד, O Sad Be-sid, again there's
וסד בסיד, Ve-sad Be-sid, או סד בסיד, O Sad Be-sid, but anyway,
or plaster the wall with סיד, Sid, your friend's wall, or plaster
the pit in which these are being kept in with plaster in
order to protect the friend's wall. Anyway, the point is that you
have to keep it away from the wall, not that you have
to keep it away from the boundary line. טעמא דאיכא כותל, Taama
De-ika Kotel, the reason you have to distance it is because. There
is a wall. הא לית כא כותל, Ha let ka kotel, if
there isn't a wall, סומך, someich, you can go right up to
the boundary line. That certainly seems to be the case. Everything in
the משנה mishna seems to be that there's only a problem when
there is this other object that you have to that you can't
damage, but it's not a fundamental obligation to stay distant from the
boundary line. So the גמרא gemara says לא, lo, no, that's not
necessarily the way to read it. כי לית כא כותל נמי לא
סומך, Ki let ka kotel nami lo someich, even if there isn't
a wall you can't put this stuff right up to the boundary
line. ואלא מאי קמשמע לן, Ve'ela mai kamashma lan, so why does
it say keep it away from the wall? הא קמשמע לן דהני
קשו לכותל. Ha kamashma lan de'hani kashu le'kotel. It's to explain to
you what is the problem with these things. The problem with these
things is the scenario of the wall. The scenario of the wall
illustrates that these things are why these things are potentially, you know,
damaging objects, you know, because they will cause damage to a wall
and that's why you have to keep them away from the boundary
line. So we describe the scenario of keeping them away from the
wall because that's the basic problem. The problem is that they can
damage a wall. But because that's the problem, because you have to
keep them away from a wall, you also have to keep them
away from the boundary line even if there is no wall, so
you don't compromise your friend's ability to build his wall. Okay, so
it's illustrating to you what the basic problem is, but the object
then leads to an obligation even when there is no wall. Alright,
so now the גמרא gemara says like this.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. מרחיקין את הזרעים ואת
המחרישה ואת מי רגלים, marchikin et hazera'im ve'et hamachreisha ve'et mei raglayim,
again the משנה, mishna, you keep the seeds and the plowing and
urinating מן הכותל שלשה טפחים, min hakotel shelosha tefachim, three טפחים tefachim
away from the wall. So same point, it sounds like only because
there's a wall. טעמא דאיכא כותל, Taama de'ika kotel, the reason is
because there's a wall. הא לית כא כותל, Ha let ka kotel,
if there weren't a wall, סומך, someich, you could put it right
up to the boundary line. גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, not
necessarily. כי לית כא כותל נמי לא סומך, Ki let ka kotel
nami lo someich, even if there is no wall, you can't put
it up to the boundary line. ואלא מאי קמשמע לן, Ve'ela mai
kamashma lan, so why did it say keep it away from the
wall? So you see where this is going.
הא קמשמע לן דמטונטא קשיא לכותל, Ha kamashma lan dematunta kashya le'kotel,
that moisture is difficult for a wall, to tell you this is
why these things are a problem because they will damage a wall
because of the liquid and whatever, or they will damage a wall,
and that's why you have to keep them distant from a wall.
Once you have to keep them distant from a wall, you have
to keep them distant from the boundary line so as not to
compromise your friend's ability to build a wall. So again, these are
just the concrete examples, or you know, this is the source of
the problem, but it translates into a legal obligation that would apply
in all cases. Okay, we're going to go through the whole משנה
mishna like this. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear.
ואת הריחיים גמל מן השכב שהן ארבע מן הרכב. Ve'et hareichayim gimal
min hashechev shehen arba min harechev. If you're making a mill, so
then you have to keep the away from the wall three טפחים
tefachim from the שכב, shechev, which is the lower sort of stone
of the mill, and four טפחים tefachim from the רכב, rechev, which
is the upper stone of the mill, which is more indented into
your property, it's not as wide, it's narrower than the lower stone.
Anyway, again, this is distance from the wall. טעמא דאיכא כותל, Taama
de'ika kotel, that the reason you have to keep this millstone away,
this mill away is because of the wall. הא לית כא כותל,
Ha let ka kotel, it sounds like if there weren't a wall
סומך, someich, you could go up to the boundary line. לא, Lo,
not necessarily. כי לית כא כותל נמי לא סומך, Ki let ka
kotel nami lo someich, I could tell you without a wall you
also can't put it up to the boundary line. ואלא מאי קמשמע
לן, Ve'ela mai kamashma lan, so why did it say keep it
away from a wall?
What's it teaching you? הא קמשמע לן דתירייא קשיא לכותל, Ha kamashma
lan detiraya kashya le'kotel, that תירייא, tiraya, which probably means like the
trembling of the ground, of the earth, that's caused, the vibrations are
damaging to a wall, and that's why these are a problem. And
that's the source of the problem is that they will hurt a
wall. But once that's the source of the problem, you have to
keep it away from the boundary line as well. Of course, also
the other thing you learn from this, in addition to the logic
behind why you have to keep these things away, is that then
it allows you to more apply it to other cases. Now we
understand moisture's a problem, vibrations are a problem, heat is a problem.
So we're not going to limit it to just the concrete cases
of the משנה. mishna. We would apply it to any parallel cases
as well. So it's important to know what the specific concrete concerns
are, even if the translation is you have to be distant from
the boundary line regardless. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara continues. תא
שמע. Ta shema. ואת התנור שלשה מן הכליה שהן ארבע מן השפה.
Ve'et hatanur shelosha min hakilya shehen arba min hasafa. Again the משנה,
mishna, an oven you have to stay three טפחים tefachim away from
the lower part of the of the plaster, the way רש"י Rashi
explains it, the wider part of the plaster, or תוספות Tosafot says
from the stomach of the oven, the fatter part of the oven,
שהן ארבע מן השפה shehen arba min hasafa which is four טפחים
tefachim away
from
the narrower part of the oven. Again, this is away from the
wall. טעמא דאיכא כותל, Taama de'ika kotel, the reason is that there's
a wall. הא לית כא כותל, Ha let ka kotel, if there
isn't a wall, סומך someich presumably you could go right up to
the boundary line. So the גמרא gemara says לא, lo, כי לית
כא כותל נמי לא סומך, ki let ka kotel nami lo someich,
no, you wouldn't be allowed to do it even if there weren't
a wall. So why did it say away from the wall? ואלא
מאי קמשמע לן, Ve'ela mai kamashma lan, what's it teaching you? הא
קמשמע לן דהבלא קשיא לכותל, Ha kamashma lan de'havla kashya le'kotel, that
the heat is, you know, is a problem to a wall, and
that's the underlying basis for this, that would apply to other things
that give off heat. But again. that would translate into an obligation
to keep it away from the boundary line whether or not there
is a wall. Okay, תא שמע, ta shma, לא יפתח אדם חנות
של נחתום, lo yiftach adam chanut shel nechtom, now we're going to,
coming up משניות, mishnayot, do not open up a baker's shop ושל
צבעים veshel tzavaim or a dyer's shop that they dye wool תחת
אוצרו של חברו. tachat otzaro shel chaveiro. Do not open it up
directly below your friend's warehouse because
there's a question here, is the problem the smoke or heat? תוספות
tosfot says that it's the heat, not the smoke. So תוספות tosfot
says that it is, let me just double check תוספות, tosfot, right,
then תוספות tosfot says it's the heat, but one way or another,
either the heat or the smoke of these enterprises, these business enterprises
are going to go into your friend's warehouse and destroy his stored
up wheat and whatever else he's storing in his warehouse. So therefore,
you cannot do it directly under your friend's warehouse. This is a
later משנה. mishnah. ולא רפת בקר, velo refet bakar, or neither can
you actually do
a what do you call it, a stable, obviously the smell of
the excrement. So in these cases טעמא דאיכא אוצר, taama deika otzar,
the reason that you cannot put these in certain places is because
they will get to your friend's storehouse. היכא דליכא אוצר, heicha deleika
otzar, if there's no storehouse around where the heat or the smell
or the smoke can do damage, עביד, avid, so you would be
allowed to do it. So it sounds like you fundamentally would be
allowed to do this right up at the boundary line if there's
no concrete thing that you are threatening. So the גמרא, gemara, of
course it could have given the same reason it's given until now,
which is no, you're not allowed to, but it's just giving even
if there is no thing, but it's just giving you the concrete
example, but the גמרא gemara actually gives a different answer. The גמרא
gemara says דירה שאני, dira shani, and this is an important different
answer. You know what? In this case you're right. In this case
you are allowed to build right up to the boundary line, other
cases you're not, but this case you are if there's nothing that
you're directly threatening. Why is that true? It's true because this is
a דירה, dira, a domicile. Now technically speaking, it's not a domicile,
it's a store,
it's a barn, but nevertheless, interestingly, sort of like zoning laws, there's
one type of thing about doing certain activities. You can't do this
activity right up to the boundary line or even I guess building
something, you can't build a cistern right up at the boundary line
where we can limit that and say that has to be done
only in certain ranges within your property, but things that are considered
to be basic structures you are allowed to do right up to
the boundary
line as long as you're not directly threatening something else, as long
as there is no store, no warehouse that you're directly threatening. If
you look at רש״י, rashi, fourth line from the top, רש״י rashi
says דירה שאני. dira shani. חנות ורפת בקר דירתם של אדם הם
ואין לנו לאסור דירתו עליו אלא אם כן הזיק מוכח. chanut verefet
bakar diratam shel adam hem ve'ein lanu le'esor dirato alav ella im
ken hizik muchach. So there we're not going to limit your ability
to build these basic structures unless they are directly causing damage. Now
of course then we will. If there is actually a warehouse, we
won't let you build your stable or your bakery or whatever you
want. Similarly,
you can't go ahead and build a building directly in front of
somebody else's windows, that's an issue we discussed before. But this issue
of can you build it at the border line if nothing yet
exists on the other side of the border line, nothing that's a
problem, do you have to pull back because in not to compromise
the other person's ability to build right up to the border line,
here we're saying even if normally the answer is yes, when you're
dealing with something like a structure, like a type of a living
place, then the answer is no, we are not going to make
that demand from you as long as there's nothing you're directly threatening,
you can build up to the border line. Okay, so the גמרא
gemara now clarifies this or continues with this. It says דירה שאני.
dira shani. דיקא נמי, deika nami, now that also can be inferred
from the language of the משנה mishnah that it's a special case
because it's a דירה. dira. דקתני עלה, dekatani alah, because the ברייתא
braita clarifies on this משנה, mishnah, משנה mishnah coming up, אם הייתה
רפת בקר קודמת לאוצר מותר. im hayta refet bakar kodemet le'otzar mutar.
By the way, it says the
ברייתא, braita, if the stable was there first, then you don't have
to worry even if your friend wants to go ahead and make
a warehouse. As long as your stable was there first. Now that
idea that if you're there first it's not a problem is a
general rule which we will sort of see. But the point the
גמרא gemara is making here is it never teaches this rule by
anything else. The ברייתא braita only spells this out by the case
of the דירה, dira, doesn't spell it out by the cistern or
by the other things, by the pile of plaster or all those
other issues. It only spells it out by this. Why? Because what
it's coming to tell you is this case it's okay if you
were there first, even if you were there first and build it
right up to the boundary line because in another case maybe I
was first but I
violated this question. If you're not allowed to build build it up
to the boundary line, it's possible you could be there first but
you could be in violation. How could you be there first and
be in violation? You built it up to the boundary line. Okay,
but in this case, even though that's normally true and you could
be first and be in violation and maybe we would make you
move your things, in this case if you were first, you get
to keep it there, even if you built up to the boundary
line, because in this case you're allowed to build up to the
boundary line. Okay, so that's the basic point here, you're right, you
are, but that's because this case is an exception. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. תא שמע Tashma come and hear, לא יטע
אדם אילן סמוך לשדה חבירו אלא אם כן הרחיק ממנו ארבע אמות.
Lo yita adam ilan samuch lesade chavero ella im ken hirchik mimeno
arba amot.
You cannot go ahead and plant a tree right next to your
friend's wheat field or grain field unless you are four אמות amot
distant. Now why do you need four אמות? amot? Until now we've
been talking like about three טפחים tefachim or something of that nature.
So the גמרא Gemara says ותניא עלה vetanya ala we taught on
this, ארבע אמות שאמרו כדי עבודת הכרם. arba amot sheamru kedei avodat
hakerem. The reason is that's the amount of space you need to
work a vineyard. Now of course your tree is not a vineyard,
תוספות Tosafot just says yes, but the standard four אמות amot comes
from the vineyard, but here it's true as well even if it's
just an orchard, which is, you know, you cannot, as opposed to
if you had a wheat field, right? If you have like the
edge of your wheat field, you can go ahead and bring your
plow, you don't have to enter into your friend's neighboring field in
order to plow the wheat at the edge of your field. You
put your plow in the middle and you plow all the way
up to your edge. But to work a vineyard or to work
an orchard, you have to get at the outskirts and you have
to work around, you know, in order to pick, in order to,
I don't know, weed or whatever it is you're doing, you have
to get on the outside of where the edge of your trees
are, the edge of your vines are. So therefore if you make
the edge of your trees or your vines right up against your
friend's wheat field, you are going to almost necessarily walk into his
field to tend to your trees. So we can't allow that. So
we demand that you go ahead and you pull back four אמות
amot to give yourself that space that you're going to need at
the over, you know, after the edge of the trees in order
to do the work necessary for the trees. Fine, that's the הלכה.
halacha. Now, but once again we see this is only a requirement
if a wheat field actually exists there. If no wheat field exists
there, presumably it would not be an issue. So the גמרא Gemara
says טעמא משום כדי עבודת הכרם הא לאו משום כדי עבודת הכרם
סמוך. Taima mishum kedei avodat hakerem ha lav mishum kedei avodat hakerem
samuch. Now
it sounds like if it were not because of the need to
sort of operate, actually I said that differently because if you're going
to wind up going into the field then here it should be
a problem like always because you know you shouldn't be walking into
your friend's
field. But if it were not for the extra space needed עבודת
הכרם avodat hakerem to tend to your trees, then in principle, if
that weren't the case, you could go right up to the edge.
So הא לאו משום כדי עבודת הכרם ha lav mishum kedei avodat
hakerem if it were not because of that, סמוך samuch you could
go right up to the edge. ואף על גב דאיכא שרשים דקמזקי,
veaf al gav deika sharashim demazkei,
even though there would be roots of your tree that would go
underground into the other guy's field, presumably you wouldn't have to be
concerned about that.
So this is actually, right, this seems to be that we're not
concerned about the roots, we're only concerned about you actually trampling in
the guy's field. So why are we not? So it shows you
can go right up to the boundary line and you don't have
to be concerned how that might compromise the other person's ability to
do things in his yard. Okay, so this actually seems to be
evidence that you are allowed again, that you are allowed to go
right up to the boundary line even if you compromise what might
be going up in the yard. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
הכא במאי עסקינן דמפסיק צונמא. hacha bemai askinan demafsik tzunma. We are
talking about a special case. We're talking about a case that there
is a rock that goes right along the boundary line and presumably
goes underground as well and therefore there's no concern about the roots.
And since there's no concern about the roots, the only thing you
have to be concerned about is this עבודת הכרם. avodat hakerem. But
that's why you would be allowed to go right up to the
boundary line otherwise because there is no roots that are going to
pass under. Of course if there is this rock, why exactly you
have to be concerned about עבודת הכרם avodat hakerem because there's a
rock there but maybe you could go on your friend's rock and
work your כרם kerem and we don't want you doing that. Anyway
the גמרא Gemara says דיקא נמי דקתני סמוך לגירסא היה גדר ביניהן
זה סמוך לגדר מכאן וזה סמוך לגדר מכאן. dayka nami dekatani samuch
legirsa haya geder beinehen ze samuch lageder mikan veze samuch lageder mikan.
So here we have a similar story. If there's a wall between
them, you can do your vineyard right against the wall and his
wheat field right against the wall. And once again the question becomes
one minute, why is that allowed? What about the roots? Again this
is really a question it seems independent of אביי Abaye and רבא
Rava because it sounds like even if he has a wheat field
you're allowed to do it. So regardless of the question about what
if there's nothing in your friend's yard, here you have a question
why you allowed? What about the issue about the roots? So the
גמרא... Gemara... And again there's a question here of the גרסא, girsa,
but according to the גרסא, girsa, הכא נמי דאיכא צונמא, hacha nami
de-ika tsunma, so here too that there we're talking, obviously we're talking
about a special case that there is a rock, and that's why
you're not concerned about the roots. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute. אי הכי אימא סיפא. ei hachi eima seifa. If that's true,
what do you do about the end of this? היו שורשיו יוצאים
בתוך של חבירו מעמיק לו שלשה טפחים כדי שלא יעכב
המחרישה. hayu shoreshav yotsim betokh shel chaveiro mamik lo sheloshah tefachim kedei
shelo yaakev hamacharesha. If the roots did wind up going underneath your
friend's property, then your friend is allowed to basically dig into the
ground three טפחים tefachim deep and cut off all the roots in
order so as to not get in the way of his plowing.
So how did that happen? אי דמפסיק צונמא, ei de-mafsik tsunma, if
we're talking here that all of this is allowed to go right
up to the wall, you know, if there's no concern of trampling
in your friend's field, and the reason it's allowed is because there's
no concern of roots because of the rock, then how can we
say that, "Oh, but if there are roots, if the roots did
get there, then you do this." I thought there were no roots,
I thought there was a rock. So the גמרא Gemara gives the
obvious answer: מאי מבעיא
התם? mai mibaya hatam? If there's a rock, how does the roots
get there? הכי קאמר, hachi kaamar, here's how you read it. ואי
לאו צונמא, ve-ilav tsunma, but if there weren't a rock, or you
could say even if there were a rock somehow the roots managed
to get through, והיו שורשיו יוצאים בתוך של חבירו, ve-hayu shoreshav yotsim
betokh shel chaveiro, and then it went in, then מעמיק לו שלשה
טפחים כדי שלא יעכב המחרישה, mamik lo sheloshah tefachim kedei shelo yaakev
hamacharesha, then go three טפחים tefachim in. Okay, but the basic פשט
pshat here is is that while all of the evidence seems to
show that the only need to distance is when there is something
concrete that you are threatening, nevertheless what we are reading it to
say is is that that's the source of the problem, but that's
why you have to distance yourself even regardless of that other thing.
The one case where you don't have to distance yourself when there's
no other thing that you're threatening is the case of some type
of like an edifice, like a store or a or a stable
or the like. And this case here, you're allowed, this case actually
seems to be a challenge to both, that you're allowed to make
an orchard or whatever right up to the wall, and what about
the concern about the roots? Even if the guy's got a wheat
field going already there, we had to make a special case where
there were some type of a rock that prevented the roots from
spreading. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא שמע,
ta shema, מרחיקין את האילן מן הבור עשרים וחמש אמה. marchikin et
ha-ilan min ha-bor esrim ve-chamesh ama.
So this is a big distancing. You've got a tree, and here
we are concerned about the roots, so a tree will spread its
roots, presumably we're concerned it spreads its roots up to עשרים וחמש
אמה, esrim ve-chamesh ama, which right is a lot. It's like, you
know, what is it, like 40 feet. Anyway, so if you're going
to plant a tree, you have to keep it away from your
friend's cistern up to עשרים וחמש אמה. esrim ve-chamesh ama.
טעמא, taama, now again, the reason for the distancing is, דאיכא בור,
de-ika bor, because there's a cistern. הא ליכא בור סמיך, ha leika
bor samikh, if there was none, you could put your tree right
up against, or at least within the עשרים וחמש אמה, esrim ve-chamesh
ama, and you don't have to be concerned that you are compromising
his ability to build a cistern. So the גמרא Gemara says, now
by the way that raises interesting questions, because maybe it's one thing
to say I have to go three טפחים tefachim into my property,
four אמות amot into my property before you have something, but it's
a big, I think it would be a big question that even
רבא Rava who says that you have to go into your property
even if nothing is on the other side, would say that that
would mean you'd have to go עשרים וחמש אמה esrim ve-chamesh ama
into your property if there's nothing on the other side. So, you
know, there's got to be a limit. So maybe the absence of
somebody having a cistern, I can make trees closer to the boundary
edge. But anyway, but the גמרא Gemara asks that question. According to
רבא, Rava, why why are we saying only if there's a cistern?
Even without a cistern, shouldn't you have to keep it away from
the boundary line? So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי הכי, ve-ei hachi,
so the גמרא Gemara says, כי ליכא בור נמי לא סמיך. ki
leika bor nami lo samikh. No,
even if there is no cistern, you have to, you cannot put
your tree right up to the boundary line, interest- and presumably you'd
have to keep a full עשרים וחמש אמה esrim ve-chamesh ama away.
והא קא משמע לן, ve-ha ka mashma lan, so then why is
it telling us the case of the cistern? דעד עשרים וחמש אמה
אזלו שורשים ומזקו לבור, de-ad esrim ve-chamesh ama azlu shoreshim u-mazku le-bor,
to tell you again, this is the source of the problem, that
roots can spread up to עשרים וחמש אמה esrim ve-chamesh ama and
threaten a cistern. Because that's the source of the problem, you have
to keep your tree עשרים וחמש אמה esrim ve-chamesh ama away, even
if there is no בור. bor.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי אימא סיפא, ei hachi eima
seifa, let's look at the end of this. ואם אילן קדם לא
יקוץ. ve-im ilan kadam lo yakots. If the tree was there first,
you don't have to cut it down. Okay, so one minute, what
does the tree was there first mean? Presumably it means the tree
was there first within עשרים וחמש אמה. esrim ve-chamesh ama. Because if
the tree was there first but more than עשרים וחמש אמה esrim
ve-chamesh ama away, of course you're not going to cut it, there's
no concern about the roots. Okay, so how could the tree have
been there first within עשרים וחמש אמה esrim ve-chamesh ama if according
to רבא, Rava, and it there legitimately, so it doesn't have to
be cut down, how could it legitimately have been there within עשרים
וחמש אמה esrim ve-chamesh ama if according to רבא, Rava, even if
you're there first, you have to keep this distance away from the
boundary line? ואי לאו סמיך, ve-ei lav samikh,
and if you are not allowed to put it against the boundary
line, היכי משכחת לה? heichi meshkachat lah? How could your tree have
been there legitimately first that now you're allowed to keep it? So,
the גמרא Gemara says... It says, כדאמר רב פפא, k'd'amar Rav Pappa,
like רב פפא Rav Pappa says in another case, בלוקח, be'lokayach, we're
talking about a purchaser. הכא נמי בלוקח, hacha nami be'lokayach, here too
we're talking about a purchaser.
What does that mean? It means that you had your tree there,
and then your tree was in the middle of your field, and
then you sold, you divided your field down the middle, and you
sold the other part to somebody else. So now, your tree was
legitimately there, because when you planted the tree, it wasn't next to
anything, it was סתם stam in your field. Now, because of the
way you divided your field and you sold the other half to
somebody, either you sold the part without the tree or you sold
the part with the tree, it doesn't matter, the person now who
has the tree has the tree there, it's near twenty-five אמות amot
to the new boundary line, but nothing wrong was done when the
tree was planted, it was completely there legitimately. Okay, so therefore in
that type of a scenario, you have no responsibility,
the guy can't demand you cut it down, you have no responsibility
to cut it down, the tree was there legitimately. But if the
boundary line was already there, there was a neighboring property already there,
רבא Rava would say, and you planted it within twenty-five אמות, amot,
then you would be in violation even if the friend had done
nothing yet on his side and you would have to then cut
it down and move it. Okay, so that's an important difference here
about a scenario where you would never be in violation because it
was always there and then you subdivided the property.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, ta
shma, מרחיקין את המשרה מן הירק, marchikin et hamisreh min hayerek,
you have to keep the משרה, misreh, which is the place
of like of a soaking flax, which apparently would create very bad
smells, you have to keep it away from a vegetable garden. ואת
הכרשים מן הבצלים, v'et hakrashim min habetzalim, and כרשים, krashim, which are
cress, away from onions. Okay, which I don't know, cress can damage
onions I guess, I would think the opposite, onions are more pungent,
but anyway. ואת החרדל מן הדבורים, v'et hachardal min hadvorim, and you
have to keep mustard seed away from the bees. You know when
you buy honey, you know it'll tell you, oh these bees, you
know it's honey and they took from the nectar of these types
of plants, lavender or whatever it has special flavor. So you do
not want the bees to be eating off of mustard and then
making their honey, that will produce bad honey. So you have to
keep your mustard seed away from the bees and whatever the appropriate
distance is. Anyway, once again it seems like the whole obligation to
separate is because this thing is concretely there, not just because it
might be there, not just it's a separation from a boundary line
even if nothing is on the other side. So the גמרא Gemara
says, טעמא דאיכא ירק, ta'ama de'ika yerek, the reason is because there
actually are vegetables there. הא ליכא ירק, ha leika yerek, in the
case of the whatever, in the case of the flax, הא ליכא
ירק סמיך, ha leika yerek samich, could you do it? No, כי
ליכא ירק נמי לא סמיך, ki leika yerek nami lo samich, even
if there's no vegetables you can't do it. והא קמשמע לן, v'ha
kamashma lan, so then why say it? דהני קשו אהדדי, de'hani kashu
ahadadi, to tell you the same point, this is what the nature
of the problem is. Okay, and therefore that's why since your flax
soaking affects vegetables, keep, and you have to keep it away from
vegetables, therefore would say רבא, Rava, you have to keep it always
away from the boundary line regardless. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אי הכי אימא סיפא, ei hachi eima seifa, let's look at the
end about the bees. ורבי יוסי מתיר בחרדל מפני שיכול לומר לו
עד שאתה אומר לי הרחק חרדלך מדבורי הרחק דבוריך מחרדלי שבאים ואוכלים
את גלגולי חרדלי. v'Rabbi Yossi matir be'chardal mipnei she'yachol lomar lo ad
she'ata omer li harchaik chardalcha midvorai harchaik dvoraycha michardali sheba'im v'ochlim et
gilgulei chardali.
So
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says no, you do not have to keep
the mustard away from the bees, because you can tell the guy
with the bees, you're saying to me that I have to keep
my mustard away from your bees because they're injuring your honey, I'll
say the back to you, keep your bees away from my mustard
because they're coming and they're eating my mustard. So therefore, I'm no
more מזיק mazik you than you're מזיק mazik me, and I don't
have to distance myself. Now this is very interesting for two reasons.
One, you know, we know and we've said before and we're going
to say again, that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi basically might say in
general, על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו, al hanizak leharchaik et atzmo, that
the person, it's not the מזיק's mazik responsibility, it's the ניזק's nizak
responsibility. Here he's not saying, look, I don't care if I'm damaging
you, it's your responsibility. He's saying very specifically by the bees and
the honeys
and by the bee and the mustard, I'm no more damaging you
than you're damaging me. So that's not a general point that the
damagee has to remove himself, that's just here in this specific case
where we're equally damaging one another. That's point number one which the
גמרא Gemara will get to. It seems like a limited position of
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. Point number two
is that the obvious answer to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is like
who came first? You know, if the bees were there first then
you're bringing the mustard, you're damaging me. If the mustard was there
first and I'm bringing the bees then I'm damaging you. Maybe though
the easiest case is that we're assuming that they're both coming to
do it at the same time, and if we're both coming to
do it at the same time, you know, then we could just
say why should I be the one to move, you should be
the one to move? Or. תוספות Tosfos also points out, you know,
and this is an important question to keep in mind, which is
how easy is it to move the enterprise? Right, like a tree
is a major, to demand somebody to move their tree once their
tree is planted, that's like pretty, you know, that person would clearly
have to be at blame at fault, right, because he's cutting down
a whole tree, you know, or uprooting it and replanting it's a
whole major thing. You know, תוספות Tosfos says that the thing about
the honey and the mustard, like so the bees and the mustard,
you know, maybe those are not enterprises that are as difficult to
move. So then maybe, although this is still a little surprising, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosei could say, even if I'm coming with the mustard
after your bees, you know, you should just as well go ahead
and move your bees because your bees are damaging my mustard. But
you know, even there the question you would ask is that even
if it's easy to move the bees, it would seem that the
person who comes second is the one who more has to justify
themselves. And if that person is causing a damage, even if the
damage goes both ways, that person doesn't have a right to go
ahead and do that near the other person's bees. Okay, so that's
an interesting question. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei here number one is not
framing it as a ניזק nizek's responsibility, he's saying we're both מזיקים,
maziks, number one. And number two is it sounds like he would
say that even if the mustard guy came second, which is definitely
a חידוש. chiddush. But anyway, why is this relevant for us? It's
relevant for us for exactly this reason that it sounds like the
guy with the mustard came second. And according if you say that
you always have to say distance, well let's take a look. ואי
ve-ee let's turn the page. ואי, ve-ee, I see it's a nice
short דף. daf. One of the reasons it's here so short and
you got this big תוספות Tosfos is because it's a very hard
דף daf to just parse. So we're going to do our best,
okay, but that there are some logical sort of jumps here. Anyway,
the גמרא gemara says like this. ואי דלא סמיך, ve-ee d-lo samich,
if it were if you in general, like רבא, Rava, were never
allowed to keep the person your enterprise right near the boundary line,
היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachas lah? So how did you ever get
this case, right? It's because, you know, how how could רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei basically say, hey, you know, I'm not damaging you anymore
than you're damaging me? If the first person was never able to
put it to the boundary line, then you sort of are always
avoiding the issue, right? Then the first person with the bees always
kept his bees away from the boundary line. So, right, remember what
we said? We said when we say this idea of distancing, we're
not saying that it's only when the concrete thing already exists, you
always have to distance because that thing might come about. Okay, then
who are we primarily talking about? Then we would always be talking
to the first person as much as the second. So if you're
coming to do your bees, don't do them near the boundary line
because that's going to compromise the guy's ability, you know, to do
the mustard, so, and vice versa. So according to, you know, according
to so if the משנה mishna is saying that the guy with
the mustard had to keep himself distant, right, I think I said
that in the reverse. Let's go again. If the משנה mishna says
the guy in the mustard has to keep himself distant because of
the bees, and what that actually means is is that even if
there are no bees, you have to keep yourself distant because of
because there might be bees. Okay, so basically the guy with the
mustard is keeping himself distant. So why is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei
saying that you could say that the guy with the bees, hey,
you know, your bees are just as much damaging me? You know,
what do you mean? They're not damaging you. You never got your
mustard right up to the boundary line. Okay, so like, you know,
what is this idea that it's like one of them is saying
to the other, since neither of them can go up to the
boundary line, they both have to stay distant? Now, there actually would
seem to be an answer to that. The answer to that is,
right, who has to be distant? If you view one person as
clearly the מזיק mazik and the other person as clearly the ניזק,
nizek, then the point is, let's say we say the the mustard
is doing the damage, the bees are the ones being damaged. So
if that's true, then even if there's nothing there yet, if I'm
coming to do bees, I could do it right up to the
boundary line because I'm not, you know,
doing, you know, influencing you because I'm not creating any damage on
your side, right? Whereas if you're coming to do the, what do
you call it? If you're coming to do the mustard, even if
nothing is there yet, you have to stay away because you're the
one who's doing the damage. So that's what the rabbis would say.
The rabbis would say the guy with the mustard has to stay
back because even if nothing is there yet, because if there were
bees, he would be doing damage to the bees. And comes along
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says, no, each
one is equally damager and damagee. So it's not just the guy
with the mustard has to stay back, if the guy with the
bees came first, he would have to stay back so his bees
shouldn't damage the other guy's mustard. All right, so it's possible that
we could be debating this not when something is already there, but
in anticipation of something being being there and trying to decide who
has the responsibility to keep away from the boundary line. So this
is one of the reasons again this גמרא Gemara is very complicated
to understand what exactly is bothering it. Okay, but what the גמרא
Gemara is seem to be saying is that it sounds like that
what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is sort of saying is, is that
the mustard guy is saying to the bees, hey buddy, you move.
So it sounds like the bee enterprise is already, you know, right
up against the boundary line. And how did that happen, if you're
not allowed, you know, if you have to stay away from the
boundary line? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: So,
אמר רב פפא בלוקח. Ammar Rav Papa bilokayach. So here's where רב
פפא Rav Papa said, we're talking about a case where originally it
was, there was no boundary line, somebody basically went ahead and started
his bee enterprise, and then sold the field, half of the field.
And now the guy in the other half wants to make his
mustard. Okay, and that's where the Rabbis are saying, okay, so I
got my bees right up to the boundary line because of, because
I was allowed to do it. Nobody owned the other field yet.
Now that you own the field, you have to keep away. And
then רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi comes and says, no, you know, you're
just as much damaging me as I'm damaging you and you've got
to move your bee enterprise. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי
בלוקח, ee bilokayach, if we're talking about a case of purchase, מאי
טעמא דרבנן? mai taama derabbanan? What's the reason of the Rabbis? Now,
what do you mean what's the reason of the Rabbis? We just
said. The reason of the Rabbis is because you were there first
with your bees, let the other guy move. So this again, this
is why there's this big תוספות. Tosafot. So רש"י Rashi says what
it means is, I don't know why we're saying this, but רש"י
Rashi says it means the flip, that it's not that you started
with the bees, you started with the mustard. And you went ahead
and you started with the mustard, and then you sold let's say
that mustard with the field with the mustard to somebody else. And
now you want to go ahead and you want to do your
bee enterprise. So the Rabbis say, okay Mr. Mustard Guy, even though
you, you know, you've got to move, you're damaging my bees. And
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, no, the mustard guy says to the
bees, you move your bees, they're damaging my mustard. Fine. So now
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi position makes a lot more sense, because the
mustard was there first, and it was there legitimately. So the mustard
was there first and it was there legitimately because the whole field
was one big field initially. Now it split into two, somebody wants
to make the bees. So now that's what the גמרא's Gemara saying
is, if the guy with the mustard was there legitimately, you really
understand רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. So why would the Rabbis say the
mustard guy has to uproot his mustard and move it? מאי טעמא
דרבנן? mai taama derabbanan?
So the גמרא Gemara says, ועוד, ve'od, מאי טעמא דרבי יוסי? mai
taama derabbi Yossi? אפילו נשרפא ירקא נמי. afillu nishrefa yarka nami.
So also why does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi now say if the
mustard guy was there first and now we really understand רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yossi, hey I was here first, I'm okay, you move your
thing. Okay, so if that's true, it's not because the bees are
damaging the mustard. So in that scenario, רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi position
makes so much sense just because the mustard there guy was there
legitimately. So then it shouldn't be limited to a bees and a
mustard case. Even in a case about the flax and the vegetables,
where it's clearly it's the flax damaging the vegetables and not the
other way around, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi should say if the flax
guy was there first and he was there legitimately because the field
used to be one and then it got split into whatever, then
even if he's causing damage to the other guy, he shouldn't have
to move because he was there first. Okay, so it's all very
complicated. But anyway, the point is, is that it sounds from this
case that, you know, that somebody did it close to the boundary
line and that's, and not like the approach of רבא, Rava, which
is that you're not allowed to do it close to the boundary
line. If you reinterpret it to say it's a case of לוקח
lokayach and that made it legitimate to do it close to the
boundary line, then it's really hard to understand the other position here,
then the guy who was there legitimately shouldn't have to move at
all and you can't understand the רבנן Rabbanan that say you have
to move. So now I'm going to read this next line the
way תוספות Tosafot does because it makes the whole part a lot
more simple. And he has the word here אלא. Ella. So תוספות's
Tosafot next line is the following: אלא אמר רבינא. Ella ammar Ravina.
So rather רבינא Ravina says, you know what, the way תוספות Tosafot
reads this, we are completely revamping רבא. Rava. קסברי רבנן, Kasavar Rabbanan,
the רבנן Rabbanan who disagree with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi hold, על
המזיק להרחיק את עצמו. al hamazik leharcheek et atzmo. So רבא Rava
until now, רבא Rava has been saying that you are not allowed
to build up to the boundary line even if there's nothing there.
So now the way תוספות Tosafot is reading this, this is reading
quite a bit into the גמרא. Gemara. But the way תוספות Tosafot
is reading this is to say, you know what, we tried to
say that the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, whatever, goes
whether according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, whether according to the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Really it's not true. Really according to the רבנן Rabbanan that
say it's the מזיק's mazik responsibility, so therefore it's only when you
are really causing נזק. nezek. So you are allowed to go ahead
and to build, you know, your thing right up to the boundary
line as long as there's nothing else yet on the other side.
Okay, the only problem is when there is... something on the other
side. Because it's a problem about you being identified as a מזיק,
Mazik, it is not a problem when there's nothing on the other
side. The only case that אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, this is
the way תוספות Tosfos reads it, were arguing
was
about digging a cistern because you might remember the גמרא Gemara earlier
said that when you dig a cistern that is directly damaging the
other guy's property like the act construction act and the act of
digging and the weakening of the ground, that's directly damaging the other
person's property. It doesn't matter that there's nothing on the other side.
But all these other cases, you know, because obviously all the evidence
has been this way that the only problem is when there's concretely
something on the other side. Fine, you're right. It's because you're a
מזיק Mazik and when you're not identified as a מזיק, Mazik, even
though because you're doing this, if the guys later want to do
something, he can't go right at the boundary line, he has to
be the one to move away, nevertheless right now you are not
a מזיק, Mazik, there's nothing you're damaging and you're allowed to do
it. Okay, now and and that's actually so fine, you're right, and
the same here too. You went ahead and you are going ahead
and you were doing your, you know, your doing your you want
to plant your mustard, if there's nothing on the other side, גזונטערהייט,
gezunterheit, plant your mustard right up against the boundary line. You're right,
that is what the רבנן Rabbanan say. It's only when there are
bees that the רבנן Rabbanan come along and say ah, now there
are bees, you're going ahead to plant your mustard, now you have
to keep away. Okay, so we are we are accepting the פשט
pshat of all of this. רבא Rava is basically doing a big
retraction. He's limiting himself. When can you not do at the boundary
line? When you're digging a hole because that causes direct damage. But
otherwise, if there's nothing there, you're allowed to go up to the
boundary line. So the Rabbis are saying if there are no bees,
go ahead and plant your mustard. If there are bees, don't plant
your mustard, you're a מזיק. Mazik. Fine. Moving on. And now we're
going to understand what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is saying back.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא ela
so it says קסברי רבנן על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו kasvari Rabbanan
al hamazik leharchik es atzmo מכלל דרבי יוסי סבר על הניזק להרחיק
את עצמו. michlal d'Rabbi Yossi savar al hanizak leharchik es atzmo. So
it's a funny גמרא Gemara because you know, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
by the bees is basically saying we're מזיק mazik one another. But
because of the way the גמרא Gemara framed it, על המזיק להרחיק
את עצמו al hamazik leharchik es atzmo is saying oh, so you
mean to say that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi would say which we
do say otherwise, but it doesn't sound that way here, that it's
always the ניזק's nizak responsibility, and if it's always the ניזק's nizak
responsibility, even if you've got your beehive, I can go ahead and
do my mustard and you have to move? It's your responsibility to
move? Is that what we're saying רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is saying?
That's why I'm allowed to do my mustard up to the boundary
line? So the גמרא Gemara says אי על הניזק אפילו משרא וירקא
נמי. ei al hanizak afilu mishra v'yarka nami.
So why is he limiting himself to the mustard and the bees?
That he should be saying you know, it's not just because we're
damaging one another. Even if you have your vegetable garden, I should
be able to do my flax right up to the boundary line
and you move your vegetables. It doesn't sound like רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi is saying that. It sounds like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is
saying it's because we're damaging each other. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא לעולם פשיטא רבי יוסי נמי על המזיק סבירא ליה. ela l'olam
peshita Rabbi Yossi nami al hamazik svira lei. Not like we generally
assume. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi also says it's fundamentally the מזיק's mazik
responsibility. Okay, that makes a lot more sense. It's the מזיק's mazik
responsibility. But here the question is who is the מזיק? mazik? והכי
קאמר ליה רבי יוסי לרבנן. v'hachi ka'amar lei Rabbi Yossi l'Rabbanan.
Here's what he's saying. תינח משרא וירקא דהני מזקי הני והני לא
מזקי הני. tinach mishra v'yarka d'hani mazkei hani v'hani lo mazkei hani.
I get the flax and the vegetables. Flax damages vegetables, vegetables don't
damage flax. So in that case I would agree with you. You
would have to,
if the vegetables were already there, you'd have to do your flax
enterprise elsewhere. אלא חרדל ודבורים ela chardal u'devorim
but mustard and bees? תרווייהו מזקי אהדדי. tarvayhu mazkei ahadadi. They both
damage one another. And presumably that means that it also doesn't matter
who comes first. So even if you've got your bee enterprise going
on and the Rabbis say oh, this guy's got a bee enterprise
going on, you have to stay distant, again because we're assuming if
there's nothing there you're okay with your mustard. But no, he's got
a bee enterprise, you keep your mustard distant. So says רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi no, my mustard is damaging your bees the same degree
your bees are damaging my mustard. And surprisingly, even if I come
second, you know, I can go ahead and plant my mustard here
and you have to move your bees. Okay, so that's the question,
whether you view it that they're damaging one another and also how
that impacts who's first and whether it makes a difference who's first
and who's second. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ורבנן v'Rabbanan what would the Rabbis say back? דבורים בחרדל לא
מזקי ליה. devorim b'chardal lo mazkei lei. Give me a break, the
bees don't really damage the mustard. אי בזינתא לא משכחת לה. ei
b'zinta lo mishkachat lah.
If it's by eating the seed, that doesn't happen, bees don't eat
the seed. אי בטרפא ei b'tarpa if it's about the leaves, הני
פריצי hani paritzei so the leaves grow back, that's not a real
damage. Okay, so again that's interesting. It sounds like they're debating what
not I wouldn't say exactly the מציאות, metzius, but the threshold of
whether the damage is significant enough. But I would say that even
if it does damage, you're coming second, you keep away. Anyway now
the גמרא Gemara continues. וסבר רבי יוסי על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו.
v'savar Rabbi Yossi al hamazik leharchik es atzmo. One minute, so we've
pointed out that since רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi limits himself to mustard
and bees, it sounds like he's only arguing because they are damaging
one another. Okay, but he would not say that normally the ניזק,
nizak, the one being damaged, has a responsibility to move. Is that
really true? ותנן, Ve-tenan, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabi Yose omer, אף על
פי שבור קודמת לאילן לא יקוץ, af al pi she-bor kodemet le-ilan
lo yakotz, שזה חופר בתוך שלו וזה נוטע בתוך שלו. she-ze chofer
be-toch shelo ve-ze noteia be-toch shelo. Right? This is a big חידוש.
chiddush. I've got my cistern in my property. You plant a tree
after my cistern was there,
and
your tree's roots are definitely going to spread and damage my cistern.
You can basically say to me, you know, sorry Charlie, you know,
yes I was here second, yes my tree will damage your cistern
and not the other way around. I'm the מזיק, mazik, I came
second, but I can do what I want in my property. You
go ahead, you move your pit. Okay? So you see clearly רבי
יוסי Rabi Yose says it's על הניזק להרחיק, al ha-nizak leharchik, not
על המזיק להרחיק. al ha-mazik leharchik. And if that's true, you should
say the same by the flax and the vegetables and you shouldn't
need the special reason of the bees and the honey. So גמרא
Gemara says fine. אלא לעולם, Ela le-olam, you're right. רבי יוסי... Rabi
Yose... רבי יוסי Rabi Yose says you're right, all of the הלכות
halachot we've said so far, unless again it's a case of direct
damage where רבי יוסי Rabi Yose would agree, but all the cases
we've said so far, you can do whatever you want in your
property even if you're coming second, even if you're the damager, as
long as it's not direct and the other guy has to move.
So why is רבי יוסי Rabi Yose saying what he's saying about
the bees? So the גמרא Gemara says, ולדבריהם דרבנן קאמר להו. u-le-divreihem
de-rabanan ka-amar lehu. He's saying to the Rabbis, even within your position
you should concede to me. לדידי, Le-didi, as far as I'm concerned,
על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו al ha-nizak leharchik et atzmo that the
one being damaged has to move, ואפילו משרה וירקא לא בעי רחוקי.
ve-afilu mishra ve-yarka lo baei rehuki.
And even if it's flax and vegetables, the guy with the flax
can come second, he doesn't have to distance himself, and the guy
with the vegetables is the one that has to move. I can
do whatever I want in my property as long as I'm not
directly damaging you. That's my position. אלא לדידכו דאמריתו על המזיק, Ela
le-didchu de-amritu al ha-mazik, but you say no, no, the damager has
to distance himself and have to limit himself within his own property.
תינח משרה וירקא, Teinach mishra ve-yarka, fine, I get that case when
you can clearly label who's the מזיק, mazik, like the flax and
the vegetables.
דהאי מזקי להאי והאי לא מזקי להאי, De-hai mazki le-hai ve-hai lo
mazki le-hai,
one damages the other and not the other way around. אלא חרדל
ודבש, Ela chardal u-devash, but the mustard and the honey. תרוייהו מזקו
אהדדי, tarvaihu mazku ahadadi, but the mustard and the honey they are
damaging one another and the bees are damaging one another. So in
that case you should concede to me that it is not only
the responsibility of the guy with the mustard. Okay now again you
might wonder who came first, but okay, at least whatever, somehow it
should be a shared responsibility.
ורבנן, Ve-rabanan, and the Rabbis say back, no, דבש לא מזקי לה,
devash lo mazki leh, no, the bees are not really... are not
really damaging the mustard. וחרדל לא מזקי לה. Ve-chardal lo mazki leh.
אי בגינזא לא משכחת לה, Ei be-ginza lo meshkachas leh, it doesn't
eat the seeds. אי בטרפא, Ei be-tarfa, if it's the leaves, הדרי
פארי, hadri parchi, they grow back again. So phew, that was a
lot. So what did we say? So the first thing we said
is we've reinforced this idea that there's this debate between רבי יוסי
Rabi Yose and the רבנן Rabanan of whether על המזיק להרחיק al
ha-mazik leharchik or על הניזק להרחיק. al ha-nizak leharchik. רבי יוסי Rabi
Yose lets somebody do whatever they want in their own property. You
are master of your domain and the other person has to distance
themselves if they don't want to be injured, with the one exception
of when what you're doing causes direct injury in the other guy's
property. Apropos of that, if you take a look at רבי יוסי's
Rabi Yose argument with the Rabbis about the bees and the mustard,
that the mustard was... the bees were damaging the mustard, the mustard
was damaging the bees, that was just arguing with the Rabbis within
their own position. And actually תוספות Tosafot references a תוספתא Tosefta that
רבי יוסי Rabi Yose even says this explicitly. Let me see if
I can find the תוספות. Tosafot. He says,
about eight lines from the bottom, it starts with the word פ"א
pei-alef in parentheses, it says, רבי יוסי מתיר בחרדל שאומר לו כדרך
שעשית בתוך שלך כך אני עושה בתוך שלי. Rabi Yose matir be-chardal
she-omer lo kederach she-asita be-toch shelcha kach ani oseh be-toch sheli. Okay,
that it has nothing to do with who's damaging who. It's like,
do what you want in your property, I'll do what I want
in my property. If you don't want to be hurt by it,
then you go ahead and you make whatever decisions you make. So
that's רבי יוסי: Rabi Yose: על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו al ha-nizak
leharchik et atzmo unless it's causing direct damage. The רבנן Rabanan say
no, it's על המזיק להרחיק. al ha-mazik leharchik. And within the רבנן
Rabanan of על המזיק להרחיק, al ha-mazik leharchik, it becomes interesting questions
of let's say there's nothing concretely yet that it is threatening. So
that's the whole debate of whether you could be סומך. somech. So
initially the גמרא Gemara sounded like רבא Rava was saying that for
the Rabbis you have to anticipate that the guy might want to
do something and you have to distance yourself from it even ahead
of time. The way תוספות Tosafot reads the מסקנא, maskana, רבא Rava
basically retracted. And רבא Rava said with the one exception of a
cistern where it's directly causing damage even right now, you really can
do whatever you want up to the boundary line and the only
time that you have to move
is
when there actually is something concrete on the other side. And sort
of the remaining question
that is sort
of that. Has not yet sort of been fully fleshed out is
like should it matter who comes first and who comes second, right?
Because that סוגיא sugya sort of said, if you did it ברשות,
berishut, even if you're the מזיק, mazik, you don't have to move.
And how do you get a case of doing it ברשות? berishut?
Well, one case now, one case is לוקח, lokayach, it all was
one field. But now that we said that you can do up
to the boundary line, that would be the clearer case. I did
up to the boundary line, I made my mustard enterprise. Now you
want to do your bees? Hey, that's not my responsibility. I was
here, nobody else was here. You now want to do your bees?
That's for you to go ahead and find us somewhere else to
do it. Okay, so it's a real interesting issue about balancing people's
sort of rights and responsibilities and how that sort of plays out
based on, you know, anticipating what's going to do and how you
might compromise the person's ability to act freely, which is the debate
of אביי Abaye and רבא, Rava, and then also your ability to
totally freely in your property even if that possibly will cause damage,
which is רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose position as opposed to the Rabbis
that say no, you have to like limit what you're doing in
your property if there actually is something at least concrete there that
you might actually be directly or indirectly causing damage to. Okay, so
we'll end here and pick up tomorrow.